<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the Cathedral and Metropolitan Church of St. Peter in York, January 30th, 1688/9, and published at the request of the auditors by William Stainforth ...</title>
            <author>Stainforth, William, d. 1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586978</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586978</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100572</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61248)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the Cathedral and Metropolitan Church of St. Peter in York, January 30th, 1688/9, and published at the request of the auditors by William Stainforth ...</title>
                  <author>Stainforth, William, d. 1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ... and Francis Hildyard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XXXV, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:100572:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Needham,</hi> R. R. in Chriſto P. ac D. D. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmo</hi> Archiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aed. <hi>Lamb.</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. 21. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100572:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Cathedral and Metropolitical Church OF St. Peter in York, <hi>January</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1688/9. AND Publiſhed at the requeſt of the Auditors.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM STAINFORTH,</hi> Reſidentiary Canon of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's-head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, and <hi>Francis Hildyard,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>York,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100572:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100572:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>II. CHRON. 35. 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—And all Judah and Jeruſalem mourned for Joſiah.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MOURNING ſuppoſeth Grief, as being the proper effect and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral indication of it; for though Grief is a ſecret and hidden paſſion, and inwardly ſeated in the Mind, yet, as all other paſſions, when they are ſuffered to ſwell and grow up to any conſiderable degree of ſtrength, it affects our Bodies in ſuch a ſenſible manner, as renders it apparent and manifeſt to all, who look upon us: For the Soul and the Body are ſo cloſely united together, and have ſuch a dependency and influence on each other, that their intereſts are inſeparable, and they mutually partake in each others impreſſions; ſo that whatever affects the Mind in a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome manner, and ſits heavy upon it, the Body falls under the weight, and ſhares in the preſſure and uneaſineſs of the burthen; for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100572:3"/> the grief of the mind contracts and oppreſſeth the Heart, it checks the motion of the Bloud, retards and ſlackens its Circulations; it damps and clogs the vital Spirits, relaxeth the Nerves, and enfeebleth the Animal faculties, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices and weakens them in their neceſſary ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. And from hence proceed thoſe ſad Looks and dejected Countenances, thoſe deep Sighs and heavy Groans, thoſe loud Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and effuſion of Tears, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called Mourning, and which are ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernible in all perſons, who are oppreſſed and afflicted with any conſiderable degree of Grief and Trouble of mind.</p>
            <p>So that Mourning ſignifying all the outward ſigns and ſenſible expreſſions of Grief, it muſt ſuppoſe Grief, if it is not counter feit and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as the inward and neceſſary cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>And as Mourning ſuppoſeth Grief, ſo Grief in ſome meaſure or other is the natural and common portion of all mankind. Our ſtate and condition in this world does neceſſarily ſubject us unto it, and we can no more reſiſt the impreſſions than we can prevent the cauſe<note place="margin">Job 5. 7.</note> of it. <hi>Job</hi> tells us, <hi>That man is born to trouble as the ſparks ſly upwards.</hi> By which he means, that our Nature does as neceſſarily expoſe us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100572:3"/> to ſufferings and grief, as the nature of ſparks does determine their motion upwards. We came into the world with Tears in our Eyes, and we no ſooner breath out we cry; and thoſe Infant-Tears and Ories are Ominous and Prophetick of our future ſucceeding condition, and ſadly preſage, that our continuance in the world will be like our entrance into it, and that we ſhall never want, in ſome reſpect or other, cauſe of Grief and matter of Complaint. And indeed whoever conſiders the frailty of our Nature, and the paſſiveneſs of our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, the inſtability of humane Affairs, and the uncertainty of all earthly Comforts, will find the evidence of this great Truth too bright and convincing to ſuffer a contradiction. But alas! I need not diſcourſe on the Reaſon and Philoſophy of it to gain your aſſent to it, every man's perſonal experience is a ſufficient argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for this purpoſe, and there is no neceſſity of appealing to any thing but that for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative proof and full conviction of it: For what man is there upon Earth, who has not his infelicities as well as his ſins, his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes as well as his guilts to wound and afflict his Soul? What man is there whoſe Sun is always ſo bright and ſhining as never to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100572:4"/> be over-caſt and clouded? whoſe days are always ſo calm and ſerene as never to be ruffled and diſcompoſed with any rude ſtorms and boiſterous tempeſts? Alas! what mam is there but frequently ſuffers in his private and perſonal intereſts, as he ſtands conſidered by himſelf, and without relation to the publick Community, of which he is a member? Thus how often do we ſuffer in our Health, in our Reputations, in our Eſtates, in our Friends and Relations? How often are we croſſed in our deſires, and diſappointed in our hopes, and fruſtrated in our deſigns, and deprived of our choiceſt, and moſt valuable earthly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts? But when an affliction becomes Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and is as publick and extenſive as the whole Kingdom, then every man muſt be a ſufferer on that account, and partake of the common Calamity, becauſe every man makes a part of the Nation, on which it is laid. And have not Kingdoms and publick Societies of men, conſidered as ſuch, Afflictions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes as well as private Perſons? Are not thoſe equally with theſe obnoxious to Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and liable to Loſſes? And is not the death of good King ſuch a publick loſs, ſuch a common Calamity? And can ſuch a loſs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100572:4"/> ſuch a Calamity happen, and not be regarded and conſidered? Or can it be conſidered and reflected on, and not be reſented with a quick and paſſionate Grief, with a Grief as univerſal as the Loſs, and with a Mourning loudly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative, and emphatically expreſſive of that Grief? This is impoſſible to humane Nature, except where it is ſo far hardened by Folly, or corrupted by Vice, as to become inſenſible of its moſt tender and concerning Intereſts: For it's as natural to grieve for any Good which we loſe, as it is to rejoice in the uſe and poſſeſſion of it, and our Joy and our Grief are in both caſes proportionable to the nature and importance of it. And as no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Good is of greater advantage to us than a good King, becauſe nothing is of ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and univerſal influence to the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo the Loſs of ſuch a King cannot but be lamented and bewailed by all thinking and conſidering People, with all the ſigns and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of an hearty Grief and affectionate Sorrow. And ſo the whole <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation did, when good <hi>Joſiah</hi> dyed, for my Text tells us, <hi>That all Judah and Jeruſalem mourned for Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100572:5"/>
            <p>In the diſcourſing on theſe words, I will,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider the general Reaſon which induceth a People or Nation in common to grieve and mourn for the death of a good King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider how much the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation were concerned in this general Reaſon to grieve and mourn for the death of <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider what particular and additional Reaſon they had, beſides the general one, to grieve and mourn for his death.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider our own caſe in relation to the ſad occaſion of this day's Aſſembly, and ſhew you, that though the <hi>Jews</hi> had great and extraordinary reaſon to mourn for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> yet theſe Nations had not onely as much but more reaſon, nay, ſtill have more reaſon to mourn and lament the death of our late Dread Sovereign King <hi>CHARLES</hi> I. of ever Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100572:5"/>
            <p>1. I will conſider the general Reaſon which induceth a People or Nation in common to grieve and mourn for the death of a good King. Now all Grief ſuppoſeth the Loſs of ſomething which we eſteemed and valued, and which ſome way or other contributed to our delight or our advantage: For Grief is a trouble and perturbation of Mind, which is raiſed and effected in us through the ſenſe and experience of ſuch a loſs; and therefore when we grieve and mourn for the death of any Perſon, our Grief ſpeaks the intereſt we had in his Life, and the ſufferings we feel by his Death. And as the very Make and Principles of humane Nature, by a ſtrong and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Bias, incline us to love and eſteem thoſe who oblige us by their favours and kindneſſes, who are uſefull and beneficial to us, who are the happy inſtruments of the eaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our lives; ſo the ſame Nature as ſtrongly diſpoſes us for Grief, when Death takes ſuch a dear Friend from us, and will not allow us to conſider the loſs which we ſuſtain by his departure, without a real and hearty concernment, without a ſenſible and afflictive Sorrow.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100572:6"/>
            <p>And as our Natures urge and neceſſitate us to grieve on ſuch a ſad occaſion, ſo Religion allows it; for the Deſign of Religion is not to extinguiſh our affections, but to rectifie them; not to root out our paſſions, but to reclaim and reduce them, to bring them into good order, to put them under the diſcipline and conduct of right Reaſon, and to keep them within thoſe bounds and limits which were originally ſet and preſcribed unto them. Religion allows us to love the good things of this world, in proportion to their worth and value, their conveniency and uſefulneſs, and in ſubordination to our love of God and of the things above: And it allows us to grieve for the loſs of what we love, ſo long as our Grief exceeds not the cauſes of it, nor riſeth beyond the merits of the things whoſe loſs affect us with it; ſo long as it does not grow up into Fret, and Vexation, and Impatience, nor ſallies out into Murmurings and Repinings, but keeps a juſt decorum, and due conſiſtency, with our dutifull ſubmiſſions and humble reſignations to the Will of Almighty God. Thus our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, who had no paſſions but what were natural and innocent, grieved<note place="margin">John. 11. 35.</note> for the death of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and expreſſed that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100572:6"/> Grief by ſhedding Tears, which the <hi>Jews</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted as an argument of the Love and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which we had for him. And thus may we love our Friends and Relatives, and mourn for the death of thoſe we love, without any guilt or danger, without any diſparagement to our Reaſon, or any offence to God, if we do but take care to avoid the criminal and intemperate Exceſſes of either.</p>
            <p>And if our Nature conſtrains, and our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion allows us to grieve for the death of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Friend, whoſe kindneſſes perhaps went no farther than our ſelves, or at moſt were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended but to a few beſides, how much more then for the death of a good King, whoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactions were as diffuſive as his Authority, and, like the benign influences of the Sun, ran through all the parts of the Nation, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited all the corners of the Kingdom, and gave life, and vigour, and ſpirit, to the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity: for a good King is the moſt publick and comprehenſive Bleſſing imaginable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a King derives and ſecures unto his People all the Bleſſings and Comforts which can proceed from a wife and gentle, a juſt and mercifull adminiſtration of Government: For it is inconſiſtent with the notion and nature
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100572:7"/> of a good King to govern arbitrarily, as that ſignifies governing by mere Will, Humour, and Paſſion, for that is the proper temper and character of a Tyrant, who abuſeth his juſt Authority to evil purpoſes, and inſtead of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting his Subjects, oppreſſeth them; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ruling them prudently with all his Power, turns his Power into an inſtrument of his rage and folly, and exerciſeth it upon his People, not for their preſervation but deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo makes his Government a Curſe inſtead of a Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>No; a good King is acted by other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and proceeds by other meaſures, and takes his aims and directions from other ends. He conſiders the ends for which Government was inſtituted, and his Authority given him; and becauſe both were deſigned for the Peace, and Order, and Proſperity, of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, therefore he never exerciſeth his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority but with reſpect to theſe publick ends, and in ſubſerviency to them. As he has a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and paternal care for his People, ſo in all the expreſſes of his ſovereign Power he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults and intends their common intereſt and welfare; and inſtead of governing them with the ungratefull roughneſs and ſeverity of an
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100572:7"/> imperious Lord, he rules them with the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring affections and compaſſions of an indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Father. And upon this account good Kings are in Holy Scripture compar'd to the moſt uſefull and beneficial Things and have Titles and Appellatives of Honour given them, which are borrowed from thoſe excellent Things. Thus they are call'd, <hi>The Healers of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 3. 7.</note> 
               <hi>a Land,</hi> becauſe by their wiſe and prudent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Government they apply pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per remedies to the diſeaſes and diſtempers of it, and cure the wounds and breaches which have been made in it: <hi>The Bars of it,</hi> becauſe<note place="margin">Lam. 2. 9.</note> by their watchfulneſs, and providence, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary preparations, they ſecure it from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing invaded and rifled by foreign force and violence: <hi>The Shields of it,</hi> becauſe by their<note place="margin">Pſal. 47. 9.</note> power and ſtrength they defend it from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and protect it from violence: <hi>The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11. 3.</note> 
               <hi>of it,</hi> becauſe by their prudent care and conduct, and diſcreet management of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick affairs, they ſupport the peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of it, and preſerve it from ſinking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confuſion and falling into diſorder by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Seditions and Commotions. They are ſtyled <hi>Sheepherds and Fathers,</hi> which import not onely their power and dominion over
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100572:8"/> their People, but alſo their watchfull care and tender affections for them: Nay, as if every thing upon Earth were too ſcanty and little to make up a juſt Compariſon, and to ſet forth the mighty uſefulneſs and excellency of their Perſons, they are <hi>ſtyled Gods,</hi> which would have been accounted a piece of Court-bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy, if we had not had the Authority of Holy Scripture to warrant the uſe of it. And indeed a good King may in ſome ſort be juſtly reckon'd an earthly God, becauſe he repreſents the heavenly One, not onely in his Majeſty and Power, but alſo in his Love and Goodneſs, and in thoſe invaluable bleſſings and benefits which he procures for and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys to his People: And therefore no wonder that ſuch a King is dear to his Subjects and gains ſuch an intereſt in their affections, and extends his Empire to their very Souls, which no earthly force can reach, no humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er can ſubdue, and makes him reign over their minds as well as their bodies, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth his Throne in their hearts, which is a more ſure and laſting eſtabliſhment than his Sword can give him.</p>
            <p>And then it is as little wonder, That when ſuch a King dyes, the whole Nation is ſtruck
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100572:8"/> with Grief, and invaded with Sorrow, and bewails the ſaid Accident with all the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Expreſſions imaginable; for the Love which they had for his Perſon, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which they enjoy'd under his Government, and the frightfull apprehenſions which they may entertain on ſuch a dreadfull change, are ſo many powerfull cauſes to produce an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Grief in their Minds, and to croud their Eyes with Tears, and to fill their Mouths with dolefull Complaints and Lamentations; for all ſuch changes are dangerous, and full of hazard; and though they do not always prove fatal and miſchievous to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet there is always reaſon to ſuſpect that they may; for where there is no cauſe to hope that things can grow better, there is always cauſe to fear that they may grow worſe: And therefore whenſoever a good King dyes, Fear and Love combine and unite, to afflict all his Subjects with a pungent and hearty Grief, and People of all Nations and all Religions have felt and experienc'd this troubleſome Paſſion on ſuch a moving and affecting Occaſion, and have own'd and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd it by ſolemn and ceremonious Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; and ſo in particular, <hi>All Judah and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100572:9"/> mourned for Joſiah:</hi> which brings me to the</p>
            <p>II. Which is to conſider how much the Jewiſh Nation were concern'd in this general Reaſon, to grieve and mourn for the death of <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The general Reaſon which induceth any People to mourn for the death of a good King is (as I have ſhewn you) the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe various Bleſſings and manifold Benefits which they reap'd and enjoy'd under the Exerciſe of his Sovereign Power and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his Government: For theſe Bleſſings are ſo near and concerning, and do ſo ſenſibly touch us, that we cannot conſider the death of the happy inſtrument of them without being affected with a real and hearty Grief for the Loſs of him. Now that <hi>Joſiah</hi> was ſuch a King, and ſuch an Inſtrument, will appear, if we conſider that He was endu'd with all thoſe natural, ſpiritual, and moral Excellencies and Perfections which are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to make up and complete the juſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a good King, and to render him the greateſt Bleſſing to his People. For,</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Joſiah</hi> was a King of an excellent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100572:9"/> and Wiſedom, which in others is the fruit of long experience and much obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the acquiſt of ſtudy and induſtry ſeem'd to be innate to him, and born with him: For he gave early proofs of a Wiſedom ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, as no leſs diſtinguiſh'd him from his Subjects, and ſet him above them, than the Dignity of his regal Office and the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of his ſupreme Power. For as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to reign when he was but eight years old, ſo within eight years after he entred upon his Government; the Wiſedom, which was ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to himſelf, brake out in a moſt conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous manner, and the firſt Eſſays of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in that which is both the indication and beginning of true Wiſedom; for the Scripture tells us, <hi>That in the eighth year of his reign, while</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34. 3.</note> 
               <hi>he was yet young, he began to ſeek after the God of David his father:</hi> Afterwards he proceeded to conſider the Actions of his Predeceſſors, and according to the dictates of his own Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the counſels of the Elders, (which, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> obſerves, he always took along with him,) he rectified their errours and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes with as much exactneſs and circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as if he had been an old man, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and imitated what he found eſtabliſhed by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100572:10"/> them with good advice, and ſettled upon juſt and weighty reaſons.</p>
            <p>2. He was a King of extraordinary Piety: For his Soul was filled with a juſt and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull ſenſe of God, which diſcover'd it ſelf in ſuitable Acts of Holineſs and correſpondent Practices of Religion and Goodneſs through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his whole Converſation. He had a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and active Zeal for the Glory of God, and could not endure that his Honour ſhould be given to another, or that he ſhould have any Corrivals and Competitours in his Worſhip; for he purg'd the Land from Idolatry by demoliſhing the Altars of <hi>Baal,</hi> and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Groves, which were the places of their Idolatrous Worſhip, and breaking their carved Images, which were the Objects of it, and putting to death their Prieſts, who were the Inſtruments and Miniſters of it, and reducing the miſ-led People to a juſt ſenſe of their duty and ſervice which they ow'd to the only true God, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> He repair'd the decays and ruines of the Temple of the Lord at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> with extraordinary diligence and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, and adorn'd it not onely with materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Ornaments, but with the ſpiritual Beauty of Holineſs, by reſtoring the publick Worſhip
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100572:10"/> of the true God to its ancient Glory and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Nor can we doubt, but that the whole courſe of his Life was uniform, and in all the parts of it conſiſtent with his ardent and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Zeal for God's Worſhip; That it was entirely govern'd by the ſame holy Principles, and directed by the ſame holy Rules, and was in all reſpects a bright and illuſtrious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſincere Piety and true Religion; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we conſider the glorious character which the Holy Ghoſt gives us of him in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for there we are told, <hi>That he did that</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 22. 2.</note> 
               <hi>which was right in the fight of the Lord, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in all the ways of David his father, and turned not aſide to the right hand or the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. He was a King of ſtrict and impartial Juſtice; for he govern'd his People by juſt and equal meaſures, ſuch meaſures as were the legal ſtandards of Right and Wrong, and were eſſential and fundamental to that Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conſtitution: For though God inſtituted the Jewiſh Monarchy, and ſet Kings over them, and veſted their Kings with a Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Power, yet he did not leave the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of this Power to the boundleſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Liberty of their own Wills, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100572:11"/> them certain Rules, which they were inviolably to obſerve, both in the Deciſion of Controverſies concerning Civil Right and Property, and in the management and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Criminal Cauſes. And theſe Rules are known by the Name of the Judicial Law of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in contradiſtinction both to the Moral Law, which reſpected things of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and univerſal Obligation, and to the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law, which related to the poſitive and inſtituted Worſhip of God. And the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Kings had no Authority to diſpenſe with or abrogate this judicial Law, either in whole, or in part, but were bound by the Command of God to conform themſelves unto it as the ſtanding and unalterable rule of their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And therefore when the King came to his Throne, and enter'd upon his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, He was commanded <hi>to write a Copy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 18, 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>of the Law with his own hand, and to reade in it all his days, that he might learn to fear the Lord his God, and to keep all the words of this Law, and theſe Statutes to doe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Joſiah,</hi> out of a juſt regard to the Authority of God, and a tender reſpect to the Welfare of his People, contains himſelf in the exerciſe of his Sovereign Power within thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100572:11"/> bounds which God had ſet him, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters his Government according to thoſe Laws which God appointed to be the conſtant<note place="margin">2 Kings 23. 25.</note> and fixed rules of it; for ſo we are told, <hi>that like unto him was there no King before him, that turned unto the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might, according to all the Law of Moſes, neither after him aroſe there any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where by all the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt be meant the judicial as well as the moral and ceremonial Laws, and conſequently this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character of <hi>Joſiah</hi> muſt imply his exact and punctual Obſervance of that in matters civil and political, as well as his ſtrict Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the other in things of a moral and ceremonial nature.</p>
            <p>And what greater Bleſſing could a Nation enjoy, or wiſh for, than ſuch a King, who was ſo admirably qualified and fitted for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and who in his Government kept punctually to the legal conſtitution of it, and inviolably obſerv'd all the publick Rules which either related to the Worſhip of God, and the duties of Religion, or to the civil Rights and Properties of the People? And therefore the Death of ſuch a King could not be reckon'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100572:12"/> any otherwiſe than a publick Loſs, nor could the Notice of it be received by any thinking perſon without ſuch a paſſionate and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Grief, as was ſuitable to the nature and moment of the Conſequences which depended on it. And accordingly when good <hi>Joſiah</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the whole Nation was ready to dye with Grief too, ready to faint and ſink under the ſenſe of their Loſs, and the weight of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; for as their Loſs was extraordinary, ſo their Grief was ſo exceſſive, and ſo much beyond the ordinary rate of Mourners, that it became proverbial, and the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> could not find a more proper inſtance of Grief to repreſent the greatneſs of that Mourning which the Children of the Bride-chamber would expreſs, when Chriſt their Bridegroom ſhould be taken from them, than this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Death of <hi>Joſiah</hi> was lamented; for thus he deſcribes it, <hi>It ſhall be like the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Megiddo.</hi> And indeed all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary reaſon to mourn at that extraordinary rate for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> not onely becauſe he dyed, but becauſe he dyed in that ſurpriſing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing manner. Which brings me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100572:12"/>
            <p>III. What peculiar and additional Reaſon they had, beſides the general one, to grieve and mourn for the Death of <hi>Joſiah.</hi> If good <hi>Joſiah</hi> had dyed according to the ordinary courſe of Nature, and gone to his Sepulchre, and been gathered to his Fathers, as a ſhock of corn fully ripened, and in its proper Seaſon, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> elegantly compares it; though his<note place="margin">Job 5. 26.</note> death, even under ſuch circumſtances, had been a loſs, and an infelicity, yet the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that he had lived ſo long, and as long as the forces of humane Nature could hold out, might have been a juſt abatement of their grief, and diſpoſed them to have born the Calamity with leſs Trouble, and more temper of Mind. But alas! the caſe was quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for he not onely dyed in the prime of his Age, in his full ſtrength and vigour, but he dyed too by the hands of Violence; for he was ſlain in the day of Battel, as he was endeavouring to oppoſe the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to ſtop his march towards the river <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates:</hi> For an unlucky <hi>Egyptian</hi> drew his miſchievous Bow, and ſhot a fatal Arrow, which gave him his mortal wound, and ſoon put an end to his Life, and to all the joys and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100572:13"/> delights of his people; for they could not bear the death, the untimely and violent Death, of ſuch an excellent King, without being extremely concern'd at it, and almoſt overwhelm'd with a deluge of grief and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it. And indeed the manner of his death was a juſt occaſion for ſo great a grief, becauſe it was ſo plain an indication of God's diſpleaſure againſt them, and ſo clear a Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick of Calamities and Miſeries which would follow upon it. For though Kings muſt dye like other men, and though there ſeems nothing extraordinary in the untimely and violent death of a good King, when we conſider onely, that they are made up of the ſame frail periſhing materials with our ſelves, and, with the reſt of mortal men, are equally ſuſceptive of the fatal impreſſions of a deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Violence; yet when we conſider farther, that the Providence of God does in an eſpecial manner ſuperintend and watch over good men, and in a more particular manner over good Kings, then we cannot reflect on the untimely and violent death of a Wiſe, Holy, and Juſt King, without being convinced that Heaven is highly offended, and has a dreadfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with the Nation, and has removed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100572:13"/> this great inſtrument of its Bleſſing out of the way, that ſo its wrath may break in with greater liberty, and fall down upon it with all the diſpatch and execution imaginable. And the <hi>Jews</hi> had a more than ordinary reaſon to make ſuch a judgment on the untimely and violent death of their good King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and to interpret God's permiſſion of it, as the effect of his ſore wrath, and heavy diſpleaſure, which he now ſeemed reſolved to pour down upon them in ſuch National Calamities and Miſeries as ſhould bear proportion to their own and their Anceſtours provocations. For they had been aſſured by <hi>Huldah,</hi> the Propheteſs, that the Idolatries and Impieties of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had kindled and blown up the wrath of God againſt them to ſuch a degree, that it ſhould not be quenched, but ſhould flame out upon them in Judgments as ſignal as their Crimes, and as extraordinary as their Offences which deſerv'd it: But notwithſtanding, for the ſake of <hi>Joſiah, whoſe heart was tender, and who</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 22.</note> 
               <hi>humbled himſelf before the Lord,</hi> God would defer the Execution of his wrath, and not bring it upon them in his days. And therefore, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were warranted by this Prophecy to eſteem the life of their King as the ſureſt preſervative
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100572:14"/> of their own, and to look upon his Perſon as an happy Skrene, which interpoſed between them and the diſmal terrours of God's juſtice, and kept off his deſtroying hand from ſeizing and laying hold on their guilty Nation, ſo they had reaſon to conclude from the manner of his death, that God was quite wearied out with their provocations, That his Patience and Long-ſuffering were utterly exhauſted, and that he was now ſending down upon them all thoſe tremendous judgments, which their Prophets had ſo clearly foretold, and their ſins ſo loudly called for. And all men muſt own this to have been a reaſonable inference, gather'd from the manner of his death, which carried in it ſuch evident marks of God's fierce Anger and Diſpleaſure againſt them. And muſt not their grief then have been as reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable as the inference? For if they had any ſenſe of their publick loſs, and of the fatal Conſequences which attended it, how was it poſſible for them to have ſtood unconcerned, or to have griev'd leſs than they did, under ſo awakening and aſtoniſhing a Providence? No wonder then, that when <hi>Joſiah</hi> dyed an univerſal Grief ran through his Kingdom, and all his Subjects expreſſed their grief in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100572:14"/> ſuch extraordinary Mourning, as became as remarkable for its Greatneſs as the ſad Loſs that occaſion'd it. But though the <hi>Jews</hi> had great and extraordinary reaſon to mourn for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> yet I will,</p>
            <p>IV. Shew you, That theſe Nations had not onely as much, but more reaſon; nay, ſtill have more reaſon to mourn and lament the Death of our late dread Sovereign King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, of ever bleſſed Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And,</p>
            <p>1. What was there great and eminent, of publick Uſe, and univerſal Benefit, in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Life, and Government of King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> which may not with equal Truth and Juſtice in all thoſe reſpects be aſcrib'd to the Royal Martyr of this day? For,</p>
            <p>1. As for his Underſtanding, it was of a Royal ſize, and Princely dimenſions, and of ſuch a vaſt Capacity and Comprehenſion, as ſhew'd him ſitted for Empire and Government, as he was born to it. There are none can doubt of this, who have with any care and impartiality peruſed the Book which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and wrote in the ſtate of his Sufferings; a Book which is a Lively Image of his Royal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100572:15"/> Mind, a Perfect Tranſcript of his Great Soul; a Book which contains in it not onely ſuch Exuberancy, ſuch Compaſs, ſuch Variety of delightfull Fancy, nor onely ſuch Majeſty of Style, ſuch Elegance of Phraſe, ſuch Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Language, but alſo ſuch Strength of Thought, ſuch Depth of Judgment, ſuch Reach of Apprehenſion, as uncontrollably proclaims him to have been a great Man in the modern ſenſe of the Phraſe, as that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Man of great Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>2. As for his Life; What was that but a viſible draught of practical Chriſtianity, a bright and illuſtrious example of univerſal Holineſs? for, How did all Chriſtian Graces and Vertues adorn his Royal Converſation? How did the Power and Spirit of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity appear and manifeſt it ſelf throughout the whole Courſe and Tenour of his Actions, notwithſtanding all the ſoftening Charms, and faſcinating Temptations of a Court, with which he was ſurrounded? Nor was he onely an eminent Example of thoſe Graces and Vertues which are proper to a flouriſhing and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Condition, but alſo of thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a paſſive and ſuffering State. His Chaſtity and Temperance, his Mercy and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100572:15"/> His Humility and Charity, were not more remarkable in him in the time of his Proſperity, than his Meekneſs and Contentedneſs, his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Submiſſion to the Will of God in the days of his Affliction: So that if that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Maxim had been true, That Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is founded in Grace, and Saintſhip gives Title to the power of Government, He would have had as clear and unqueſtionable a right to his own Crown and Sceptre on account of his Chriſtian Graces and Vertues, as he had on the account of his natural and legal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>3. As for his Government, it was mild and gentle, juſt and legal, agreeable to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Laws and fundamental Conſtitutions of this Nation. As he was always inclinable to pardon injuries, ſo he was always carefull to doe none; For who was ever oppreſs'd by his Power or injur'd by his Authority? Whoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties did he invade, or whoſe rights did he uſurp? Whoſe Ox or, whoſe Aſs did he take? Or who ever could truly complain of any wrong which he did them?</p>
            <p>Indeed there were one or two Paſſages in his adminiſtration which make a loud Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry in the Nation, and were improv'd to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100572:16"/> moſt malicious and deſtructive purpoſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. But whatever Cauſes or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels miſ-led him into thoſe Errours and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, it is plain that they did not proceed from any deſign which he had of overturning the legal Eſtabliſhment, and ſetting up an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Power in the room of it, as his malicious and implacable Enemies falſly accus'd him: For never any Prince could be more liberal in his Conceſſions, and indulgent in his Grants, than he was, to allay the jealouſies, and remove the fears of his People. For to aſſure them that he deſir'd no more power than the Laws al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him, he was content to enjoy leſs; and parted with ſome of his own legal Rights to convince his Subjects that he had no intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to uſurp upon theirs, and diveſt himſelf of ſuch eſſential and fundamental Prerogatives of his Crown as did in ſome meaſure Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him, that ſo he might let them ſee how far he was from any thoughts of governing as a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Now how happy might theſe Nations have been under the indulgent Government of ſuch a Prince, if they had but underſtood their own happineſs, and would but have been conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have enjoy'd it, as their duty, and their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100572:16"/> intereſt oblig'd them? But as it is not in the power of the wiſeſt and beſt of Kings to make their Subjects happy againſt their own wills, ſo if Subjects will be querulous and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under Peace and Plenty, if they will be unaccountably fearfull and unreaſonably jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and fanſie Hobgoblins and Bugbears ready to ſeize and devour, when there appears nothing but their Guardian-angel to defend and protect them: If they will be ſeditious and turbulent under the beſt of Governments, and the beſt of Kings, their Follies are both their Sins and their Puniſhments, and as they ſtand accountable to God and Man for their Guilts, ſo they may thank themſelves for the miſchievous Conſequences of them. But though our contemptuous thoughts of a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ingratefull behaviour under it, may keep us from reaping the happy and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table effect of it; yet they cannot change the Nature, nor leſſen the Worth of it; but the Enjoyment of it will be a Happineſs, and the Deprivation of it a Loſs, notwithſtanding our miſtaken opinions, and ſcornfull neglect, or deſpightfull treatment of it. And therefore though many rejoyc'd at the death of our Royal Martyr, and others were ſtupidly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100572:17"/> at it, yet all wiſe and good Men conſider'd it as it really was, a Publick Loſs, and reſented it as a general Calamity, and were affected with a pungent Grief, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd a paſſionate Sorrow for it: And they had extraordinary reaſon for ſo doing, as will farther appear if,</p>
            <p>2. We conſider the Manner of his Death; for his Death was neither in the common courſe of Nature, nor according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary periods of it, but it was violent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely; for he fell by the hands of cruel and bloudy-minded Men, and was raviſhed from us, when in all appearance he might have lived to a far longer date, to have been the bleſſed inſtrument of much Glory and much Happineſs to theſe Kingdoms: For by the healthfulneſs of his Conſtitution, and the ſoundneſs of his Vitals, he ſeem'd to have been deſign'd for a long Life, and in all probability his Moderation, and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Sobriety, which he practis'd on all occaſions, might have lengthned his days very nigh theſe of ours, if not to them. But he was too great a Bleſſing for ſuch an ingratefull and ſinfull People to enjoy any longer; and therefore God ſuffers him to fall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100572:17"/> into the bloudy hands of his implacable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and to be cut off by them; that ſo the Nation might be involved in thoſe Confuſions, and groan under thoſe Miſeries, which the provoking guilts and impieties of it ſo abundantly deſerv'd. And all Men had great reaſon to apprehend beforehand thoſe diſmal Evils which ſoon followed his Death, when they conſider'd the Manner and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of it: For that God ſhould ſuffer ſo Holy a King to be ſo inhumanely treated, and ſo barbarouſly murthered, could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from nothing but his hot-burning Wrath againſt the Nation, and his immoveable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to pour down his heavy Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. And the Event ſadly demonſtrated the reaſonableneſs of ſuch pre-apprehenſions; for when he ſuffer'd, our Religion and our Laws ſuffer'd with him, and the Government both in Church and State expired and dyed in the very ſame moment with him: For then our Holy Religion was baniſhed from our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the Miniſters of it driven into Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or forc'd into Priſons, and the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of deſolation ſtood in our Holy Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Then Hypocriſie pull'd off its Mask, and Atheiſm appear'd barefac'd, and Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100572:18"/> grew impudent, and Sacrilege laid its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring hands on all holy Things: then innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Swarms of new and unheard of Sects ſprang and grew up among us, and walked abroad in their uncouth Forms and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Shapes: Then Popery prevail'd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd, and ſeduc'd many weak and unſtable Souls, and gained more Proſelytes in thoſe dark times of trouble and confuſion, (as ſome have made the computation,) than in all the peacefull Reign of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the ſecond. So that Cardinal <hi>Richilieu</hi> ſeems to have had ſome grounds for that Maxim of his, <hi>viz.</hi> Till the Monarchy of <hi>England</hi> was chang'd into a Common-wealth, there was little reaſon to hope for the return of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Then our Laws were either laid aſide, or turn'd againſt themſelves, expounded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to their own ruine, and the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who adhered to them, and ſo were executed in no other ſenſe, than in that in which their Royal Fountain and Guardian was executed, that is, by being deſtroy'd. Thus you ſee how the manner of our King's death was an Index of God's fierce diſpleaſure, and a Prologue to Tragical Miſeries, which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100572:18"/> immediately ſucceeded it, and what great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Nation had upon that account to grieve and mourn for him.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, but there's ſomething more of a fadder Conſideration ſtill behind, and which extremely differenceth our Caſe from that of the <hi>Jews</hi> concerning the death of that good King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and ſhews that theſe Nations not onely had but ſtill have more reaſon to grieve and mourn for the violent and untimely death of that bleſſed Martyr, and glorious Saint, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, of ever Bleſſed Memory; and this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear if,</p>
            <p>3. We conſider the Inſtruments by which this bloudy and untimely death was effected and brought to paſs: For it was not an <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> or an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> not a Stranger or Foreigner, which ſlew him, but his own native Subjects, who by all the Laws of God and Man, by all the Ties of Oaths, and Engagements of Promiſes, by all the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gratitude and Intereſt, were bound to preſerve and protect his Royal Perſon againſt all attempts of Violence whatſoever. And if the <hi>Jews</hi> mourned ſo heavily for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who dyed by the chance of War, and by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100572:19"/> hands of an Alien from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how much more ought we to mourn for our Gratious Sovereign, who was put to death as a Criminal and Malefactour in his own Kingdom, and in the great and famous <hi>Metropolis</hi> of that Kingdom, and before the Gates of his own Royal Palace in that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis,</hi> and by the hands of his own natural Subjects? This was a prodigious Wickedneſs, a Complicated Villany, an Unprecedented Exceſs of Unrelenting and Impudent Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: It was Murther and Treaſon too, and both of them heightened to the utmoſt degree of Aggravation, by being dreſſed up in the forms and methods of publick Juſtice. And if all Murther is a crying Sin, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunes the Juſtice, and wearies the Ears of the Almighty, untill it be avenged, how clamarous muſt the bloud of innocent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty be? and how great muſt thoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be which muſt ſilence its loud Cries, and attone the Wrath which is due for it? And can this Nation then ſit down under the ſenſe and remembrance of this ſad and deplorable Evil, without being touched and affected with it, without being humbled and grieved for it, without accompanying their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100572:19"/> Grief and Humiliations with a ſincere and hearty repentance for the Guilt of this day's Wickedneſs, as well as of all other their Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? For the Guilt of this Murther was as National as the Loſs which was ſuſtained by it, and all the People of this Kingdom were acceſſory to it, either as the Inſtruments, or the occaſions of it; ſome by their actual put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to death, and imbruing their wicked hands, in his Innocent bloud; ſome by their unnatural Rebellion and Treaſonable Fighting againſt him; ſome by their cowardly Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and treacherous Unconcernedneſs; and all by their perſonal Sins and Vices, which inflamed the Wrath of God, and contributed to the general Provocation.</p>
            <p>And let us not vainly imagine that we are no way concerned for this great Evil, no way obliged to be grieved and humbled for it, becauſe it was committed Forty years ago, when moſt of us were not born, and moſt of of us, who were then born, not capable of knowing good from evil; for it being a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Sin, a National Judgment is due for it: And becauſe this World is the proper Seaſon for inflicting ſuch Judgments, we have reaſon to dread, that God will bring upon us the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100572:20"/> Judgement which is due for this Sin (if he has not already brought it) with all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Terrour, and Severity of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, except we endeavour to avert it with ſincere Humiliations and unfeigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances.</p>
            <p>Remember that it was not till Forty years after the death of our Bleſſed Saviour, that God viſited the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation; for the guilt of ſhedding his Innocent bloud, and it is very probable that very few of thoſe, who either petitioned for his Crucifixion, or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and Murthered him, were living at that time: And yet when God, after ſo long forbearance, viſited that Nation for that Sin, neither Age, nor Sex, nor Rank or Quality were ſpared, but all were involved in the ſame common Fate, and felt the ſevere effects of the Publick Calamity.</p>
            <p>Its true indeed, God provided an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for the Chriſtians to eſcape, and to fly beyond the reach of the publick Judgment; but that we may not preſume on impunity, from the Example of their deliverance, we muſt know, that they were Chriſtians not onely in Name and Profeſſion, but in Life and Practice, and their Graces and Vertues,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100572:20"/> were as ſingular and extraordinary as their Preſervation: And therefore conſider it is now juſt Forty years ſince the horrid Fact was committed, which we either do, or ſhould commemorate this day with Faſting and Humiliation, and Penitential Sorrows. And conſider farther, that the publick Affairs of this unſettled Kingdom, ſeem now to be brought to a <hi>Criſis,</hi> and to move on the point of Life and Death, of Happineſs and Miſery. How things will go, and what will be the iſſue and event of them, God onely knows; but I am ſure there is no ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and effectual way to make them go well, and ſucceed to our preſervation and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to humble our ſelves under the hand of God, to lament and bewail all our Sins, both Perſonal and National, Private and Publick; and particularly the Sin of this day, which was ſuch a ſcandal to the Proteſtant Religion, ſuch an Infamy to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſuch an offence to Almighty God: And therefore with contrite Hearts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Minds, let us pray to God, that he would deliver us from Bloud-guiltineſs, and particularly from the guilt of that Royal Bloud which we now bewail and mourn for,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100572:21"/> that ſo it may not be charged upon us or our Poſterity. And to our devout Prayers, let us add Works of Mercy and Charity, which are Sacrifices well-pleaſing to God; and throughout the whole courſe of our Lives, let us keep innocence, and doe that which is right, and upon all occaſions be followers of that which is good; and then we may hope that God, for the ſake of Chriſt, will pardon and forgive us all our offences, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us into his favour and protection, own us for his People in this World, and receive us into his Glory in that to come; which God grant for Chriſt Jeſus's ſake; To whom, with the Father and Holy Spirit, be aſcribed all Might, Majeſty, Dominion, Praiſe, and Thankſgiving, now and for ever. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100572:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
